Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Nan Findlow Papers, 1930-1995 and undated, bulk 1959-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Nan Findlow papers 1930-1995 and undated, bulk 1959-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
4.6 linear feet Extent: 405 Items
Nan Findlow was an advertising executive and entrepreneur. She was Creative Director for major retail companies, including Bamberger's and Macy's department stores, and held executive positions with the Ross Roy and J. Walter Thompson Company advertising agencies before founding her own consulting agency, Nan Findlow Creative Services. The Nan Findlow Papers span the years 1930-1995, the bulk of which document the period 1959-1967, and include clippings, photographs, advertising scripts for television commercials, print advertisements, story boards, marketing reports, correspondence, corporate memoranda, trade literature, speeches, and company newsletters. The bulk of the materials represents Findlow's time as an executive at the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), where her client assignments included American Home Products (Boyle-Midway), Chesebrough-Pond's, Lever Brothers Company, McCall's, Prince Matchabelli perfume, Revlon, and Scott Paper Company. In addition, there are brochures from Macy's and Georg-Jensen Inc., proofs, tear sheets, and artwork from L. Bamberger & Co. and Ross Roy of New York. The collection also includes writings, press releases, and account-history reports prepared by Nan Findlow Creative Services, the marketing consultant firm Findlow founded upon leaving JWT.
RL.00690
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Nan Findlow Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002 and 2004.
Biographical Note
1910 Born Nancy Findlow, Paterson, N.J.
ca.1937-1939 Apprentice and copywriter, J. Walter Thompson Company
1939-1940 Creative Group Head, The Texas Company (Texaco)
1940-1941 Manager of Publicity Department, L. Bamberger & Company (Newark, NJ)
1941-1945 Free publicity and special events, Feature Advertising Manager, L. Bamberger & Company.
1943 Initiated Bamberger's Womanpower Council (war industries recruiting program, used subsequently by the Office of War Information as a model in retail stores nationwide).
1945 Advertising Director, Bamberger's. First woman to occupy this role in the history of L. Bamberger & Co.
1948 Taught the inaugural Public Relations for Retailing evening course at New York University's School of Retailing
1951-1955 Copy Director and Creative Head of Advertising, Macy's
1955 Vice President-Copy Supervisor, Women's Copy Group, J. Walter Thompson Company
1967 President, Nan Findlow Creative Services (retailing and merchandising strategy). Associated with Bennett, Newbery & Cowan. Vice President, Barnum Communications.
1976 Andy Award of Excellence (given by the Advertising Club of New York).
1995 Feb 3 Died, Rutherford, N.J.
During her career with Bamberger's and Macy's department stores, Findlow won numerous advertising industry awards, including ones from Seklemian, the National Retail and Dry Goods Association (NRDGA) and Harvard Business School.
Collection Overview
The Nan Findlow Papers span the years 1930-1995, the bulk of which document the period 1959-1967, and include clippings, photographs, advertising scripts for television commercials, print advertisements, story boards, marketing reports, correspondence, corporate memoranda, trade literature, speeches, and company newsletters. The bulk of the materials represents Findlow's time as an executive at the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), where her client assignments included American Home Products (Boyle-Midway), Chesebrough-Pond's, Lever Brothers Company, McCall's, Prince Matchabelli perfume, Revlon, and Scott Paper Company. In addition, there are brochures from Macy's and Georg-Jensen Inc., proofs, tear sheets, and artwork from L. Bamberger & Co. and Ross Roy of New York. The collection also includes writings, press releases, and account-history reports prepared by Nan Findlow Creative Services, the marketing consultant firm Findlow founded upon leaving JWT.
The collection is organized into two series: General Files, including correspondence, clippings, and memoranda, which represents Findlow's career in market research and advertising; and Proofs & Tear Sheets, which represents some of the print advertising campaigns Findlow generated, primarily while working at JWT.
Related Material
Other materials relating to this collection may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, including the Account Files Collection, the Corporation Vertical Files, the Domestic Advertising Collection, the Information Center Records, the Review Board Records, the Sidney Ralph Bernstein Papers, the Colin Dawkins Papers, the John F. Devine Papers, the Wallace Elton Papers, the Dan Seymour Papers, and the Shirley F. Woodell Papers. In addition, materials relating to Revlon advertising may be found in the Gene Federico Papers and the Sheldon Sosna Papers. Materials relating to Lever Brothers advertising may be found in the Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records, and the David B. McCall Papers. Materials relating to Macy's Department Store advertising may be found in the Margaret Fishback Papers; other retail advertising may be found in the Giant Food Stores Advertising Circulars, and the Dayton Company Advertising Scrapbooks. Additional related materials may be located by searching the Finding Aids of the Rare Books, Manuscripts and Special Collections Library.
Subject Headings
Findlow, Nan; Georg-Jensen Inc.; J. Walter Thompson Company; Chesebrough-Pond's. Prince Matchabelli; Scott Paper Company; American Home Products Corporation; Revlon, inc.; Chesebrough-Pond's.; Lever Brothers Company; Macy's (Firm); L. Bamberger & Co; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Marketing consultants -- United States; Perfume industry; Television advertising; Ross Roy of New York; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Women in the advertising industry; Proofs; Newsletters; Clippings; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Detailed Description of Collection
- General Files Series, 1938-1981 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains materials relating to Findlow's career, including resumes, biographical sketches, business reports, speeches and articles, corporate newsletters and publications, and advertisement scripts. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical information, 1945-1995 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes clippings related to Findlow's life, resumes, testimonials, and obituaries.
  - Clippings
    - J. Walter Thompson Company News, 1955-1967 (Box 1)
      Selected issues that contain articles relating to campaigns with which Findlow was associated.
    - Marketing research articles, 1962-1974 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda on marketing research, 1967-1974 and undated (Box 1)
  - Print advertising, 1938-1981 (Box 1)
  - Television commercials--scripts and storyboards, 1959-1979 (Box 1)
    Clients include Boyle-Midway (Sani-Flush), Lever Brothers, and Scott Paper Company.
  - Writings, 1960-1966 and undated
    - 10 Ways to Ease that Pain in Your Neck, by Nan Findlow with Edward P. Whelan, M.D., F.A.C.S. undated (Box 1)
    - Drafts of an untitled speech, undated (Box 1)
    - Ending Eventlessness in Our Parents' Lives published in Family Circle Magazine, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Notes for the CW and AD who clings to the secret hope there is more excitement in the product than the client knows, 1966 (Box 1)
- Proofs & Tear Sheets Series, 1930-1967, (2 boxes)
  Contains artwork and printed proofs and magazine and newspaper tear sheets for advertising work that Findlow did for various clients, predominantly included here are those for Prince Matchabelli and Scott Paper Company. Arranged alphabetically by client and product
  - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Dry Skin Cream, circa 1959 (Box 2)
  - Georg Jenson, Inc., 1940
    - An American Institution, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Brochure, From the Collections of..., circa 1940 (Box 2)
  - L. Bamberger & Co., 1939-1940
    - Danger Men at Play, circa 1939 (Box 2)
    - Merry Christmas to All, undated (Box 2)
    - His Heart's Desire, 1939 (Box 2)
    - A Little Lady Encounters Fashion, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Neither Rain Nor Wind Nor Dates Nor School, circa 1940 (Box 2)
    - My Spanking Name Was 'Josephine', circa 1940 (Box 2)
    - Father Isn't Merely 'Father', 1940 (Box 2)
    - The Pinafore Goes Out to Play, undated (Box 2)
  - McCall's Magazine, 1967
    - Paper Wrap-up, 1967 (Box 2)
    - McCall's Treasure of Italian Cooking, undated (Box 2)
    - Summer When it Sizzles: From the Food Pages of McCall's, undated (Box 2)
  - Prince Matchabelli, 1959-1965
    - Abano Perfume Oil, 1959-1965 (Box 2)
    - Aziza, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Golden Autumn, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Prophecy, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
    - Windsong, 1960-1964 and undated (Box 2)
      Windsong was the first advertising campaign in the perfume industry to feature images solely of men.
    - Other Materials 1964 and undated
      - Charts of competitive perfume brands, undated (Box 2)
      - The House that Success Built, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Revlon, circa 1930-1940 (Box 3)
    - Salon Nail Polish, circa 1930-1940 (Box 3)
  - Scott Paper Company, circa 1953-1967
    - Color Explosion, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Family Placemats, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - New Waldorf, circa 1953 (Box 3)
    - Scott Towels, 1962-1966 (Box 3)